ONYANGO OTIENO ERICK

Date of birth: 17TH August 1987

Nationality: Kenyan

Postal Address: P.O. Box 856-00606, Nairobi Kenya

Religion: Christian

Languages: English, Kiswahili and Luo

ID number: 26330470 Passport number: A2127031 Email: otieno.erick2@gmail.com

Telephone: +254742989040/+254728363204

CAREER ASPIRATION

I have spent the last Seven years enhancing my career path in both Consumer Electronics and Telecommunication industry while developing skills and competencies in reputable international organisations. I therefore believe to be well prepared to aspire for leadership position of a substantial business unit in any Organization at country or regional level in areas of Business Development, Trade Marketing or Product management.

WORK EXPERIENCE

- 1. Robert Bosch East Africa Ltd, July 2017- TO DATE. Head of Trade Marketing-Bosch Home Appliances.
 - ➤ Tasked with formulation and implementation of sell-out strategy plans in East Africa countries of Operations (Kenya, Tanzania, Uganda & Rwanda) i.e Sales responsibility for dedicated customers pro-active development, coming up with innovative ideas on how to boost sales through strong activities.
 - Ensure that new and relevant products are launched for the country on time
 - ➤ PSI analysis to determine slow moving and fast moving stocks for efficient stock management and accurate forecasting.
 - > Implement a Marketing Plan and develop the market. In charge of management of the marketing activities and execution of marketing plans in the assigned markets.
 - ➤ Implementation of Retail initiatives such as product merchandising, POP placements, branding, incentives schemes and product launches.
 - Create and foster partner relationship in in the trade through regular Dealer and distributor meetings and business review.
 - > Product and soft skills training for the Bosch Free Standing and Built-in product categories
 - Monitoring and analysis of competitor activities for proactive action.
 - ➤ Identification of market needs regarding product, price and promotion
 - ➤ Channel expansion strategies through product listing in different channels i.e. Hyper, Electronics Specialists, and Independent Dealers, online retail etc.
 - Participate on meetings and ensure timely implementation of all defined action points
- 2. Samsung Electronics East Africa Limited, Jan 2015- June 2017.

Product Manager, Visual Display (TV and AV)

Key Roles and Responsibilities:

- Management of TV and AV product strategy, SKU management, Sales Forecasting and budget utilization, Go-To-Market strategy, Market Segmentation, Pricing Positioning and P&L management.
- Managing annual Marketing budget allocation totalling to approx. \$2M to meet Average Monthly sales of \$2.5M of both TV and AV in Kenya, Uganda, Seychelles, Rwanda, Somalia and South

- Sudan. Managed and executed quarterly, bi-annual and annual Marketing plans and ensuring achievement of set sales targets.
- ➤ Develop product master plans, adoption plans and revenue plans and execute to realize set targets through promotional activities that resonate with the Market and Consumer needs.
- ➤ Initiate and execute Launching of new products in the Market, having successfully been the involved in launching VD products such as SUHD, Curved TV, Sound bar and Gigasound products in the market.
- Tasked with doing Market research on local consumer needs in countries of operations and executing activities that resonate with Consumers in the Market, while maintaining the global brand principles of Samsung.
- ➤ Stakeholder meetings and discussions with key decision makers in many business verticals to push the Samsung Brand in key strategic Channels in the market i.e. Carrefour, Nakumatt, Naivas and Tuskys.

Trade Marketing Responsibilities:

- Monitoring, Analysing, and escalating weekly report from the Agency on market info & store issues.
- Regular POS/Channel mapping to determine Market Universe and key Channels to drive sales of Samsung VD products.
- Managing Sell-out Collection consistency to increase "Coverage & Accuracy" and making analyses on data for to determine insights for informed decision-making.
- Actively involved in KPI, Target setting & Performance management of Samsung Field Force for TV/AV products and ensuring Incentive allocation to enhance Sales of my product Portfolio.
- > Product and sales training, while ensuring proper training Calendar management and making available all necessary training materials to the field force.
- ➤ Identification and negotiation of branding opportunities in the channel and budget allocation based on ROI determination.
- ➤ Ensuring proper In-store communication on VD products through proper POSM distribution and content displays.
- Managing and ensuring proper use of all the retail assets allocated to different POS in the Market.
- > Fostering strong working and interpersonal relationships with Branch managers, Procurement and Field Force is strategic channels through regular visits and business discussions.

Achievements:

Promoted to handle a large portfolio of Visual Display products, TVs for which I have maintained No. 1 TV Market Share during my period of Product management.

3. Samsung Electronics East Africa Limited, Oct 2013- Dec 2014

Product Manager-Audio Visual (AV):

Kev Roles and Responsibilities:

- Market analysis done with regards to trends, benchmarking, competitor comparison
- > Specifying market requirements for current and future products by conducting market research
- Product selection
- Pricing strategy formulation
- ➤ Distribution strategy formulation; channel to market
- > Product documentation support
- > Supply Chain Management
- Maintain communication channels with Samsung HQ GBM's
- ➤ General product support across the board

4. Orange Telkom Kenya, 1st Nov 2012- Sept 2013

Product Manager: Orange Telepresence Services/ Orange Audio and web conference services (AWCS)

Key Roles and Responsibilities:

- Constantly analyse and update customers' needs
- ➤ Monitor competition activity

- > Monitor new possible products or features based on new technical components or services proposed by vendors
- Manage the products portfolio by:
 - Preparing end of Product life
 - Improving existing Product with new features, services and options
 - Launching new Product developments
- Manage and optimize Products' P&L:
 - Optimize costs with support of IT&N, sourcing and finance team
 - Optimize revenues by adopting right pricing structure and strategy so to grow volumes and develop market share
- > Lead Product improvement or new development by managing Time To Market (TTM) internal process
- > Prepare right commercialization tools to Sales team
- > Define and maintain products' dashboards
- Manage new features or product development projects following internal Time To Market (TTM) methodology
- Establish and maintain good relationship with IT & Network to analyse actual Product's performances, possible improvements, new features or services.
- > Establish and maintain good relationship with all other company's departments with regard to the product portfolio.

5. Orange Telkom Kenya, 16th April to 1st October 2012

Junior Voice Product Manager:

Kev Roles and Responsibilities:

- Managed the voice products portfolio dedicated to Enterprise customers: management of the full product life cycle from development to pruning; launch of product improvement or new product lines; Products' P&L optimization; Product dashboard publication.
- Constantly analysed and updated customer needs and feedback on ISDN and PSTN.
- Initiated an innovative approach on proactive monitoring of ISDN based on daily usage.
- > Product improvement/ new development i.e. improvement of service delivery of ISDN customers, hence leading to increased revenue generation.
- > Defined and maintained products dashboards on ISDN and PSTN.

Achievements:

> Promoted to manage a larger Portfolio of Orange Enterprise Products within 2 years of joining the organization.

EDUCATION BACKGROUND

- 1. Bachelor of Science in Telecommunication and Information Technology Kenyatta University, August 2008-April 2012 Second Class Upper Division.
- 2. Maranda High School,

Kenya Certificate of Secondary Examination (KCSE), Feb 2003 - Nov 2006.

Mean Grade (A Plain)

PROFESSIONAL QUALIFICATION:

1. Diploma in Professional Marketing(Level 6), Chartered Institute of Marketing (CIM Certification), Membership No: 38417848 ICE Consulting and Training, July 2015-To Date.

2. Samsung Essentials for Marketing,

Samsung Marketing Certification Program,

Licence No: 140919-0073

Jan 2014-Oct 2014

- 3. Certificate in Project Management (May-August 2012) Skillsoft Academy.
- Emobilis Mobile Technology Academy Integrated Certificate in Mobile and Cellular Technology (January 2010-May 2010) Credit
- Kenyatta University Cisco Training Academy CCNA 1 (Jan-March 2009) and CCNA 2 (August-December 2010)

LEADERSHIP SKILLS

- 1. Served as Vice Chairman and Chairman: ICT Society of Kenyatta University (2010-2011):
- > Successfully organized a one day Huawei Training of the club members at the Huawei training centre.
- Organized workshops at Kenyatta University that incorporated speakers from Craft Silicon, E-mobilis Mobile training academy, E-government and Seven Seas technologies
- ➤ Participated in the Tandaa digital content Competition of Kenya ICT Board as a team leader.
- > Organized corporate visits to Safaricom, Orange Kenya, KDN and Airtel for students' practical experience on Telecommunications Technologies.
- 2. Official representative of 4 Departments in the Great Work Place (GWP) Committee (2015-2017):
- Tasked to represent the welfare of 21 Staff members in Visual Display (VD), Home Appliance (HA), Trade Marketing (TM) and Enterprise Business (EBT) Departments.

STRENGTHS

- > Team player and Customer oriented
- Ability to work in transversal organization to deliver results to the team
- Result oriented with Excellent analytical and specification skills
- Excellent organization skills with strong attention to detail
- > Self-motivated with initiative and autonomy.

PERSONAL INTERESTS

- Participating in social work i.e. Kenyatta University Community Services
- > Travelling in different regions to learn and build diversity oriented mind set
- Exercising for body fitness and good health
- > Organizing and participating in IT events i.e. club seminars, Ihub meetings

REFEREES

Samuel Owino Odhiambo, General Manager-Consumer Electronics, Samsung Electronics East Africa Ltd, P.O. Box 27577-0506, Nairobi.

Mobile: +254707677643/+254204294063

Keval Shah,

Head of Sales and Marketing-Modern and Traditional Sales, Chandaria Industries Ltd,

Mobile: +254735327162/+254716199095

Felix O. Aron.

Regional Customer Projects Manager -Eastern Africa,

GE Healthcare,

Mobile: +254773499346